hi and welcome to living in Central
Texas I'm Andrea dudic realtor and
Associate broker with Vista Real Estate
I'm Jacob stard I'm a mortgage broker
with EDG home finance so you're curious
what a
$310,000 home um will cost you in terms
of monthly payment and overall costs in
buying well stay tuned we're going to
cover it all so if you're new to my
channel don't forget to subscribe and
like this video so that you can stay up
toate on all things real estate in
Central Texas disclaimer this is not an
offer to this is just for General
educational
purposes obviously each person is going
to be subject to their own credit check
full pre-approval and credit approval
the whole nine so this is just for
educational purposes only check out this
like new omega built home in the Groves
at Lakewood Ranch subdivision in West
Temple welcome to
10211 Becka Drive Temple Texas
76502 this home was built in
2018 it is
1882 Square ft three bed two bath it is
three-sided stone masonry with vinyl
plank siding
on the back it has the cutest pergola in
the back that's lit up so that you can
have cocktails coffee whatever you'd
like on the back
patio today we'll be giving examples of
monthly payments and closing costs
associated with conventional FHA and VA
loans conventional loans all right so if
you're a conventional buyer and you're
looking to do a 20% down payment you can
estimate your total monthly payment at
around
2275 a month that's going to include
your principal your interest your
property taxes and your homeowners
insurance each person is going to have
is going to have their own unique set of
circumstances and factors that change
and tweak
those numbers a little bit now what
about in terms of closing costs for a
conventional buyer yeah so in terms of
closing cost outside of your down
payment you're looking at anywhere from
2 to 4% as your total closing cost so
that's going to be based off of the
sales price and that's going to include
you know your property taxes your title
fees prepaid interest homeowners
insurance premiums pretty much
encapsulates all of them so for a
conventional loan this home priced at
310,000 might look like yeah so down
payment wise at 20% it's going to be
$62,000 down now if you factor in the
closing cost on top of that you're going
to expect to pay in addition to the down
payment around 6 to 12 Grand additional
on top of that depending on the actual
closing cost amount so we are currently
in a buyer Market which means that we're
able to ask the seller to give
concessions um which means give money
essentially to do things like pay your
closing costs and even buy down your
rate we can't do anything about your
down payment that is a lender
requirement so you will have that 20%
down or with the conventional loan
with's the lowest you can go if your
first-time home buyer you can go down to
at least 3% and most for a conventional
loan for conventional loans so 3% to 20%
and again the down payment you have to
pay for but we can ask the seller to
contribute towards your closing cost and
there's some little tricks in there as
realtor that I can Advocate and try and
get those for you um so that's a win-win
for everybody so that's our convention
absolutely yeah one of the big things
about being in a buyers's market and
kind of offsetting the increase in
prices and rates and all those good
things is you can have a great agent on
your side that will negotiate on your
behalf to try and cover some or all of
the closing cost in form of seller
credit essentially what discount points
mean is you're going to be charged 1% of
the loan amount to buy one discount
point so it's based on the loan amount
so in this case you're looking at
somewhere around
$2,400 for one discount point now one
discount Point does not equate to one
full interest rate Point down depending
on the market that day it might equate
to a quarter of a point to half a point
it really varies depending on every day
so we have some little tricks as
realtors for example instead of asking
for the seller to take $20,000 off the
purchase price
$20,000 off the purchase price over the
course of a 30-year note is going to be
very minimal in terms of your monthly
payment and the average buyer does not
live in their home forever and so we can
we can have that discussion where let's
let's take that 20,000 and instead of
taking it off the purchase price let's
ask for it to go towards concessions of
closing cost and rate buy down and if
you buy down the rate if we take that
same amount and buy it down two points
then you know the amount that you're
saving in your monthly mortgage because
your rate is lower is going to be far
greater than if you were to take
$220,000 off the purchase price exctly
and that's that's a really neat trick
and it calls us for a little bit of
creativity right or calls for but um
essentially what it's going to do is
that that $220,000 right is going to be
expanded over 360 months so really in
the grand scheme of things it's not that
much money whereas your interest rate is
going to be applied every single month
right so if you're able to take that
difference and use it towards a rate by
down in most cases the map is going to
work where it makes sense to use that 20
grand to buy your rate down versus
cutting off on the purchase price
absolutely okay great so let's take a
look and look at number two yep FHA loan
yeah so FHA if you're an FHA buyer you
can be looking at a 3 and half% down
payment which equates to roughly
$1,850 so that's that's a choice you can
go higher if you'd like now total
monthly mortgage payment your estimate
is going to include your principal your
interest property taxes homeowners
insurance and your mortgage insurance
will be included on FHA Loans all in
you're looking at somewhere between 25
and 2600 on your total monthly payment
and closing costs are they different at
all for an FHA buyer they are not
they're not going to differ between each
loan type so those closing costs are
pretty much set regardless of which loan
type you use okay so FHA loan we have
how much for down payment yep
10,850 down and then if you use just a
general estimate on closing cost say
somewhere around 3% you can estimate
about 8,500 to 9500 in closing cost
depending on actual values and again
that down payment cannot be paid for by
any party other than the buyer um it re
It's A lender requirement it's skin in
the game it's um it shows good faith uh
for the lender and so the the seller
cannot contribute towards that but again
we can try and make negotiations for the
uh seller to contribute towards your
closing cost number three VA loans yeah
so VA loan if you're a veteran and
you're looking to exercise your VA loan
which you've well earned you are looking
at an option of a 0% down payment it's
optional most people most veterans will
select the 0% down which is fantastic um
there's no other loan type like it it's
one of the best loan types out there um
so for a total monthly payment you're
going to be looking at about 25.50 to
2650 depending on actual values on VA
and then we'll still have the same
closing costs we can still ask the
seller to contribute to buy down your
rate and and reduce that monthly payment
a little bit again negotiable uh and
again want to put out there this is a
very broad statement but just to give
you an idea in this market of what some
numbers might look like for you and what
$310,000 translates to our in our area
yeah absolutely so if you are looking to
buy or sell a home like this if you'd
like any more information you can find
both of our contact information below in
the comments you can also book a call
with me on kendly again in the comments
um we'd love to speak with you we'd love
to discuss your particular situation and
the goals that you have for yourself or
your family again I'm Andrea dudic with
f real estate I'm Jacob stutter mortgage
broker with EDG home finance till next
time bye thanks